A Guide to the Director's Correspondence and Subject Files of the Department of Juvenile Justice, 1999-2003
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Director's Correspondence and Subject Files of the Department of Juvenile Justice,, 1999-2003
The Library of Virginia
44876
2 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Virginia. Dept. of Juvenile Justice.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and other protected information is considered confidential and restricted from public access for 75 years. Protected information includes correspondence regarding juvenile offenders or personnel issues within the department. It may be necessary for an archivist to review any unprocessed, modern record collections (those collections less than 75 years old) that may contain confidential information before the records can be used by patrons for research purposes or before any copies of records can be made for patrons. If you are planning to use these records, please contact Archives Reference Services for more details before planning your research trip.
Acquisition Information
Transfer of the Dept. of Juvenile Justice.
Historical Information
The Dept. of Juvenile Justice was created as the Dept. of Youth and Family Services on 1 July 1990 (Code of Virginia 66-1). Previously, the department operated as the Division of Youth and Family Services within the Department of Corrections. The named changed to the Dept. of Juvenile Justice in 1996. The Dept. of Juvenile Justice is headed by a Director who answers to the Governor. The department also operates under the heading of the Secretary of Public Safety.
The mission of the Dept. of Juvenile Justice is to "protect the public through a balanced approach of accountability and comprehensive services that prevent and reduce delinquency through partnerships with families, schools, communities, law enforcement, and others, while providing opportunities for delinquent youth to become responsible and productive citizens.
"The Dept. of Juvenile Justice operates the commonwealth's juvenile detention facilities, oversees delinquency, gang, and substance abuse programs, as well as group and transitional homes. Initiatives supported by the Dept. of Juvenile Justice include detention assessment and the Youth Assessment and Screening Instrument, the Detention Re-entry Project, the Juvenile Detention Alternatives Initiative, and the Ombudsman Program to assist families of incarcerated youth.
Scope and Content
Contains correspondence and subject files belonging to Carl R. Peed, acting director David W. Marsden, and Jerrauld C. Jones between 1999 and 2003. Includes both incoming & outgoing correspondence from these directors regarding personnel issues, juvenile offenders, legislation, the Virginia Wilderness Program, the Early Incentive Release Program, budget cuts, juvenile correction centers, special events, Prison Rape Elimation Act (2003), briefings, ethics, drug treatment courts, post-disposition detention, chaplain services, grants, Youth Industries, Transitional Opportunities Pogram, and substance abuse.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1999-2003.
Contents List
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1999-2003., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  Unprocessed.
  - Accounts, Dept. of. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administration and Finance Deputy Director. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Agency Briefings. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annie E. Casey Foundation. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Attorney General (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Audits/Investigations. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Beaumont. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Beaumont JCC. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Beaumont Park Issues. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bon Air JCC. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bon Air JCC Communication Tower. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Capital Outlay. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chaplain Services. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Code of Ethics/Conduct. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Comptroller. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conflict of Interest. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Corrections, Dept. of. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Culpeper. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Culpepper JCC. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Department of Correctional Education (DCE). (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Department of Labor Grant. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Director's Correspondence, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Director's Correspondence, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Director's Correspondence, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Director's Correspondence, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Director's Correspondence, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Director's Correspondence, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Director's Correspondence, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Director's Correspondence, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Disproportionate Minority Coordinator. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - DMAS. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Drug Treatment Courts. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Freedom of Information Act. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Services. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Governor's Office. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hanover. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - House Appropriations. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Human Resources. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Human Resources - DJJ. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Inspector General. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Internal Audit Unit. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Internal Audits. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Interstate Compact. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - JLARC. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Judges Correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Juvenile Correction Officers. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - LEADER Program. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Legislation. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Length of Stay. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - MacArthur Foundation. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mentorship Programs. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Association of Blacks in Criminal Justice (NABCJ). (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Natural Bridge. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Oak Ridge. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Post-D. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Prison Rape Elimination Act, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Private Providers. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Reception and Diagnostic Center. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Roanoke Retirment. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Salvatierra Case. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Social Services, Dept. of. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - State and Local Partnerships. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Substance Abuse. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Terrorist Information. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Transitional Opportunites Program (TOP). (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - VCIN/Virginia State Police. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Virginia Conservation Network (VCN). (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Virginia State Police. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Youth Industries. (Box 2, Folder 31)